Hello and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan.
And today we're gonna be learning
about different types of conversion
factors that you're gonna be
finding in chemical formulas.
So this is gonna be mainly a practice
problem video where we go through all
the different types of conversions that
you might see revolving around a chemical
formula, um, where we can try to define
all these kinds of conversion tools.
Just go through a bunch of
different practice problems.
So let's take a look.
We're gonna go through how to use
mole maps, and we're gonna be trying
to decipher and go through all these
different types of word problems.
Let's take a look.
Now, when we are doing all these
different types of problems, the
goal here is to map them out.
We want to be able to show how
we're gonna be converting our units.
Our ultimate goal is to let your
units guide your process so you
can see how they cancel out.
Now, when we're doing these conversions,
your goal is the mole, meaning that
if you can convert to moles, you
can essentially map your way to any
different type of units in a chemistry
course when it involves a chemical
reaction or a chemical formula.
The first thing is that we learned
about is when it came to moles.
Was that we are essentially having this
little simplified term that allows you
to convert between moles and atoms.
Now, what exactly did we do
and we were trying to convert
between these two different units?
Well, this is when we were using
Avogadro's number, which usually we
show by N and then an A to help show
that, which Avogadro's number was 6.022.
Times 10 to the 23rd.
Okay, so we'll put that here.
6.02, two times 10 to 23, and
that is articles per mole.
Okay?
So that was a very important conversion,
and that was something that you could, you
could flip, you could take the reciprocal
of and allowed you to simplify the number
of atoms you have in a sample, right?
Because if we take a little, let's
say the little tip of a pen, and
we were wondering how many atoms
there are on that little tip.
There are trillions upon trillions, right?
And trying to count those every
time is a little cumbersome.
That's when we use moles
to help simplify that.
Now being that when we do have moles
as well, the other thing we can
convert to was mass, being that we are
working in the laboratory environment.
We can always measure
the mass using a balance.
So how could you convert to there?
Well, that was using the term known
as molar mass, which you can gain
from anywhere on your periodic table.
Uh, so if you look at any element
that is on there, you will
quickly see that you could read.
All the different conversion
terms that are available to you.
All of them, like let's say carbon
is 12.01, one grams per mole, oxygen
is 15.99 gram or grams per mole
or that element, and you are able
to convert between all of them.
Now, what other things can
you convert to as well?
Well, we also learned about trying
to read a chemical formula and
essentially you have subscripts
within all those different values.
So those subscripts represent
the number of moles that you have
between two different species.
So the mole to mole conversion is
something else that is possible by
reading your chemical equations.
So these are from your subscripts.
So that's what allows you to go from
one substance to another, go from
a molecule and compound to maybe
an atom, maybe to a different atom.
There are bridges that exist.
Now is that all you can do is just
go to the bigger, two smaller picture
between compounds and molecules.
Well, you can also use Avogadro's
number to try to calculate the number
of compounds, the number of molecules.
You can use the molar mass to
figure out how many, how many
grams of a molecule do you have.
The map here is something that
you could use to try to figure out
how to do all your conversions.
So that way you're not overwhelmed when
you're going through all of them because
there can be a, there's a lot that you
have to go through and this is what the
goal of this video is to practice these.
We're gonna go through many
examples using our molar map.
The first problem, calculate the mass
of 0.453 moles of calcium nitrate.
The first thing you wanna
do is what is your map?
How can you try to see
what these units are?
Well, first thing is, is we are,
what exactly are we starting with?
So you can see in this problem, we are
starting with moles of calcium nitrate
and the entire, and what is your desired
in this problem is you want grams.
So how can we try to map that out?
Well, using from earlier, right,
we saw that we can go between
moles and grams using molar mass.
As usual, we wanna let our units
guide our process to set up these
different conversion factors.
So if we are starting with calcium
nitrate, the CaNO₃-II, what we need
to do is convert this to grams.
So the way that we're gonna do this
is by using the molar mass of calcium
nitrate, meaning that being that we have
our formula, which is ca NO three two.
We are going to be adding
up all of these components.
So we have 40.08 grams per mole.
We're gonna add that times two nitrogens.
So we have two of those.
And that's due to the subscripts
that are in these equations, right?
So that gets distributed
two times 14, uh, 0 0 7.
Uh, and then we're gonna add that to the
six oxygens that are in this problem.
All right, so when we have that
for all of our values, what we are
going to be getting for our molar
mass is 164.008 grams per mole.
And we're not gonna round it just yet.
We're gonna round it at the very end
of our problem so that way we, uh,
have all of our units and sig figs
correct at the end of our problem.
Now.
Where exactly do I plug this in?
How do I let the units guide my process?
Well, the thing is being that we need to
cancel our units, we would need to have
moles on the bottom and Grams on top.
Being that moles here is gonna
cancel moles of calcium nitrate.
So these are all going to cancel.
Now, being that this is molar mass,
that's gonna be, uh, essentially
our value a hundred sixty-four.
0 0 8 all over one mole.
And those will both, both these
terms all cancel leaving us
with calcium nitrate in grams.
So once we solve that, what we are going
to get is 74.33, uh seven, or sorry,
three three grams of calcium nitrate.
And we're going to round
that to three sig figs.
We get seventy-four 0.3
grams for our final answer.
Okay, so we are going to be rounding
that and what is that representing?
That is seventy-four 0.3
grams of calcium nitrate.
Let's go on to our next problem.
The what other types of things
we can try to calculate for here.
How many sodium atoms are in
3.73 grams of sodium nitride.
Map out your problem.
So what did we start with?
Well, the first thing is, is we
have one of our masses that's here.
So we have the mass of sodium
nitride, which is a molecule.
So we start with grams and
what are we gonna do with that?
We're going to convert that
to moles of Na three N.
So what do we need to first do is we need
our molar mass in order to convert that.
And then what we need to do
is be that's asking for atoms.
In this case, we have to read
the problem very carefully.
Here, atoms and molecules
are not the same thing.
They're individual
components of each other.
So what we're gonna have to then do
is do the mole to mole ratio to go
to moles of sodium base and then get
to atoms, which are our last step.
We'll use Avogadro's number.
Get to essentially how
many atoms there are.
That's a little bit of a long problem.
So let's try to take a look.
So the first thing, what we want to do
is we want to add up our molar mass.
So essentially you'll
take three sodium atoms.
Uh, so we'll do three times.
Twenty-two 0.99, add that plus one 14.007.
What we are going to get for our molar
mass is 82.997 grams per mole for our
problem now being that we have our
first value here, which is 3.73 grams,
how exactly can I cancel this out?
Because our molar mass is grams over mole.
How can we do that?
Well, one thing you are allowed to do.
Is take a reciprocal
of different fractions.
So what is a reciprocal?
Well, you can flip a fraction upside down.
Meaning it, let's say if I have the
following here, I have three fifths.
I could flip it, right?
So you don't literally wanna
flip it upside down like we
did, like I did over here.
You want to put it as five thirds
Taking your reciprocal meaning
we can do the same thing here.
If I had 82.997 grams per mole, I
can write that here on the bottom
and put one mole on top, which is
the Reciprocal of my molar mass.
Now, why is that really good for us?
Well, essentially it allows us to cancel
out Grams in this part of the problem.
Now, one thing we want to make sure that
we are doing here is that we are keeping
track of all of our different molecules.
That we have because we are
trying to get to moles of Sodium.
So our next step was to go do the mole
to mole conversion, which was to get to
sodium atoms, which for every one mole of
sodium, I have three Arthritium nitride.
I have three moles of sodium.
How did I get that?
Well, that's coming from the
subscript that is in the problem.
So it's a one to three ratio.
We're counting.
Now once we do that, our next step
is being that we have our moles of
of sodium that's equivalent to 6.02,
two times 10 to 23 atoms sodium.
And the one thing we're gonna
notice here is that, oh, all these
different terms, everything's
gonna cancel out very, very nicely.
Look how our units guided
our process to sodium atom.
So when we try to plug this into our
calculator, we're gonna take 3.73 times,
three times 6.02, two times 10 is 23.
Take that number and divide it by 82.997.
And then what you're going to get for
your answer is you're gonna get 8.1210
times 10 to the 22 atoms of sodium.
Being that we started with three sig
figs, we would need to round that
down with three significant figures.
Okay?
And that would be our final
answer for this problem.
Let's take a look at another
example of doing these
different types of calculations.
A sample of tin fluoride or tin four
fluoride contains 4.62 moles of tin.
How many moles of fluorine do you have?
What is your map?
Okay, so when we are trying
to do this problem, what are
we exactly starting with?
We are starting with 4.62
moles of tin in this problem.
So what we are going to want to
do is to go from moles of tin and
convert that to essentially moles of
fluorine in that pro, in this problem.
How exactly can we do it?
Well, once again, we can represent
this with our subscripts.
There are different conversion terms
we can actually gain by reading
this chemical equation up here.
So what can we get from that?
Well, just to represent that, just so
you can see, we can say that for every
one mole of tin, I have one mole of SnF4.
I can also say that for every four
moles of fluorine, I have one mole.
Of SNF-IV.
We can also say that for every one mole
of tin, I have four moles of fluorine.
So there's relationships within
all of these that we can try to use
to determine what exactly, how do
we want to convert, how do we want
to try to cancel out our units?
So being that we started with 0.462.
Moles of 10, what we are going to want
to do is cancel out our moles of 10.
So how do we have that?
Well, one mole of 10 is equivalent to
four moles of flooring, and we can see
that, oh, this is a pretty quick problem.
Moles of 10 cancels, moles of 10,
and what that's gonna be is 0.462
times four, uh, for our problem here.
And that's gonna give us our final answer.
So when we do that, okay, with these kind
of problems, we have to pay attention
to the terms that are being set for us.
What is the mass in kilograms of S to F?
Three, which contains 4.8,
nine times 10 to the 26 atoms.
Okay, so what exactly
does that mean by atoms?
In this case, it doesn't exactly
specify anything, and notice how it
doesn't use molecules or compounds.
So what does that mean here being, it
doesn't specify this is all of sulfur
and fluorine atoms in this problem.
Sometimes they might say like maybe
atoms, a sulfur, sometimes fluorine,
sometimes it's generic, meaning that
this is all of the atoms indiscriminately
all being placed within this problem.
So what we're going to be doing here
is we're gonna go from atoms to moles.
Of atoms.
So how many different types
do we have here, or individual
ones from our subscripts?
The one thing you can see is that,
okay, there's five different atoms
by adding up our subscripts, which is
equivalent to one molecule that is here.
So that's gonna be one mole
per for every one molecule, so
we can use that for ourselves.
Um, then what we're going to be
doing is being that once mass.
We can then say that, all right, well
one mole is equivalent to, uh, whatever
the molar mass of the compound, and
then we can, then that will give us our
grams in the final part of the problem.
So this is a little bit of a weird
one, a little bit of a tricky
one, but it's something that we
want to make sure that we can see
and try to map out for ourselves.
So the first thing let's do is
it's, let's get the molar mass done.
This is a skill that you will use a
lot in type in a chemistry course.
So you want to try to be very, very fast
when it comes to looking up your different
molar values and adding them up quickly.
So we have that 32.06 times two,
and then we're going to add that
to the molar mass of fluorine and
be that there's three of them.
What we are going to end up getting
from that, from this Part of the
problem is that we have a molar mass
of 121, uh, and a 114 grams over moles.
So this is what we're going
to be using in our problem.
We'll save that for later.
The first thing, what we're
gonna do, we're gonna start
with our number of atoms, right?
We have 4.89 times 10 to the 26 atoms.
And we're going to slowly work
our way across and try to convert
all these different units.
So we have our AVOGADRO'S number,
which is gonna go in the denominator
here to cancel atoms, and that is
equivalent to one mole of S and f.
Okay?
Now when we have that,
atoms cancels atoms.
Now we, what we're going to be doing
is we have five moles of SNF, and
that is from our different subscripts
here, and that's equivalent to one
mole of S two F or FF three, not six.
So that's our molecule and we can see
that those units also cancel, right?
So, and then afterwards what we will
then do is use the molar mass that we
got to convert moles of S two F three.
Two r grams, which from before we had,
um, for every one mole we have 121.
1 1 4 grams of S two F six.
Alright, so now that we have
that, we are going to cancel
all of our units and show that.
All right?
Now once we do this, the math here,
what we're going to be doing is
taking that 4.89 times 10 to the 26.
Multiply that by 121.114, and
then divide that by 6.02, two
times 10 to 23 times five.
You're gonna get a pretty
big mess of a problem.
Now when you get your final answer,
you should get this in grams first,
and you're gonna get 19,669 grams
of uh, S two F six in your problem.
Now being that we want the same kilograms,
we're gonna divide it that number by
1000 as 1000 grams with one kilogram, and
then we're going to be rounding that to
three sig figs again for this problem.
So you'll have 19.7 kilograms as
your final answer in the problem.
Okay, let's go on to another type
of problem that you might see.
How many atoms of oxygen are
found in 48 grams of oxygen gas?
Okay, so being that we are doing
oxygen gas problem, we're starting
with a mass, one thing you gotta
be able to identify is when is
something, what is its natural form?
So oxygen, what do you breathe?
Well, you breathe out oxygen,
but what form does it take up?
It's O2, right?
So it's one of your diatomic Gases, right?
So you remember, have no
fear of ice cold beer.
The other part of that is O2.
So what that means is for every,
uh, there are two moles of oxygen
atom inside of every one mole of O2.
So we gotta kind of keep that in
mind that there's a conversion
that's hidden in plain sight here.
The very first thing that we are
going to be doing in our road map
is that what we've done in the past
here, we're gonna start with the,
though, always a term that's given
to us, which is 48.0 grams of O2.
How do we cancel out those grams as we're
gonna be using the molar mass of O2?
So one mole of O2 is equivalent
to, uh, 15.999 times two.
So when we go through do that value,
we're gonna kind of, we're gonna
roughly just kind of round that
here just while I write it down.
So roughly about 32.00
grams over one mole.
Um, you could add it up and you'll
get about 31.99 something, but we're
just gonna round it for time's sake.
Now the big thing is here, we
wanna make sure our units cancel.
So notice how I have grams written
on top and the units don't cancel.
You wanna switch those up and kind of
make sure that you take the reciprocal
like we've been talking about.
So grams, cancels grams.
Now we want to use that conversion
term that we defined earlier, which was
one mole of oxygen is equivalent, or
oxygen gas is equivalent to two moles.
Of oxygen atom.
Now when we do that, we can see
that our units cancel again.
Great.
And now being that we want to know
how many atoms this is when we use
Avogadro's number to define how
many atoms we have in our problem.
Okay.
And then we see that atoms cancels again.
And this will give us our final answer.
When we do our math multiplication here,
we multiply all the values on top, divide
what's on the bottom, and then what we are
going to be getting for our final answer
is 1.81 times 10 to the twenty-four atoms
of oxygen when you do those mathematics.
Let's go on to our next.
Di-nitrogen monoxide, N-to
also known as laughing.
Gas is used as an anesthetic in dentistry.
How many grams of nitrogen are
in a 340 gram sample of N-to?
So being that we are starting with a
mass, the first thing that we are going
to need to do is cancel out grams.
So what's the first conversion term that
should come to mind in order to do that?
Well, this is when we
use our grams to moles.
So let those units kind of guide
your process, your thinking, right?
Grams of N two O is equivalent
to one mole of N two O.
Now what will we do after that?
So that means we need to define
the molar mass here we have for
every one mole of N two O is that
there are two moles of nitrogen.
And being that we want to
get into grams of nitrogen.
We'll have one mole of N is
equivalent to 14.007 grams of N.
So the one thing that we need to do is
calculate our molar mass of N two O.
So what we are going to do is
take two times 4.007, add that
plus 15.999 grams per mole.
And what we are going to end up getting
is 44.013 grams per mole for N two O.
We're going to plug that value in
44.013 and then we're gonna proceed
and do our calculation here where
we take three 40 times, two times
14.007, and then divide that by 44.013.
And what you will get for
your number is 216.4 grams of
NA, or sorry N for nitrogen.
Then we're going to be rounding that to
three sig figs for 216 grams of nitrogen.
Noticing like all my
problems are three sig figs.
They're not always three sig figs.
It just happens to be that
many of the ones I went over in
this video are three sig figs.
Let's go on to another problem that
we, that you could see, and this
will be your last one for this video.
Thank you so much for listening so far.
What is the volume of 7.10 moles of
sodium hydroxide, assuming a density
of 1.21 grams per milliliters.
Okay.
How exactly do we do this one?
This one is a little different,
so it's combining concepts that
have been gone over in chemistry.
So the first thing that we have, looking
at the problem and deciphering this, is
we have 7.10 moles of sodium hydroxide.
And we also have a conversion term that
was given to us, which is the density.
So how can we map out the units?
Well, we have moles and we also
have grams over milliliters.
So what's the commonality
behind those two units?
Well, one thing that we can do is
we can convert this to grams, right?
Because we have molar mass, avogadro's
number, and mole to mole ratio.
Those are your three choices.
So if we can convert this to grams.
Then what we can do is use the
density afterwards to bridge
the gap to milliliters, right?
So then what that's gonna do is it's
going to give us the units that we want.
So what do we need to define
for ourselves is we need the
molar mass for sodium hydroxide.
So let's do it.
So what we're gonna do is we're
gonna add up all these elements here.
So we have 22.99 plus 15.99.
Plus 1.008, and what we're gonna
get is 39.997 grams over moles.
And that's what we're gonna use above
for our molar mass of sodium hydroxide.
Okay, so first thing, what we said
we're gonna do is we're gonna use
our moles that we were given in the
problem, which was 7.10 moles of NaOH.
We will then put our molar mass in,
which is one mole is equivalent to
39.997 grams of sodium hydroxide.
And then what we will do is use
our density, which is a 1.21 grams,
is equivalent to one milliliter.
This is why we map out all of our
units because it allows us to be
able to make a plan for ourselves.
And the more you do this,
the easier it's going to get.
So you want to try to practice
it as much as you possibly can.
It's something that's used
throughout all of chemistry and you
want to try to get really, really
comfortable solving for those units.
Now when we plug this into
our calculators, what we will
get is 2 34 0.69 milliliters.
We are gonna once again be rounding
that to three significant figures.
'cause we started with three sig
figs, which is 2 35 milliliters
as our final answer, just keep in
mind, you know, the goal is the mole
when we're trying to map these out.
So you want to be able to use
your different molar masses when
you're trying to solve them.
Don't be afraid to just dive in there.
Try as many as you can.
Keep practicing and learn your
conversions so that you know
them on the back of your hand.
Thank you so much for listening.
I hope this video helped and please,
uh, please stick around and like,
and sub if you haven't yet to see
even more content on the channel.
Thank you so much.
I'll see y'all later.
Bye now.